Finding Aid for the L. G. Roberts (Lawrence G.) papers LSC.2328
UCLA Library Special Collections
L. G. Roberts (Lawrence G.) papers
1962-2009
UCLA Library Special Collections
Roberts, L. G. (Lawrence G.)
LSC.2328
0.4 Linear Feet (1 box)
In 1965, L. G. Roberts (Lawrence G.) successfully implemented the first computer-to-computer packet link between MIT and Systems Development Corporation (SDC). In 1966, Roberts became the chief scientist and in 1967 the director of the Information Processing Techniques Office (IPTO) of the Advanced Research Projects Agency (ARPA), later renamed the Defense Advanced Research Projects Agency (DARPA) of the United States Department of Defense (DoD). As director, Roberts was responsible for designing and managing the implementation of the Advanced Research Projects Agency Network (ARPANET) computer communications network, a research packet switching computer communications network that was the precursor to the internet. The collection contains the professional and research files of L. G. Roberts dating from 1962 to 2009 and includes publications; notes written by Roberts concerning the development of the Advanced Research Projects Agency Network (ARPANET); notes on the internet and on networked computing more broadly; professional correspondence.
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The collection was donated in December 2011 by Lawrence G. Roberts to the UCLA Kleinrock Internet History Center.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9981345163606533
Custodial History note
This collection was acquired by University Archivist Charlotte Brown for a proposed Kleinrock Center for Internet Studies (KCIS) at UCLA in 2011. The former collection number was KCIS001.
Biographical/Historical note
L. G. Roberts (Lawrence G.) was born in Connecticut in 1937, the son of Elliott and Elizabeth Roberts. After graduating with his BS (1959), MS (1960), and PhD (1963) in Electrical Engineering from Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT), Roberts began work at MIT's Lincoln Laboratory, where he carried out research on computer networks. In 1965, Roberts successfully implemented the first computer-to-computer packet link between MIT and Systems Development Corporation (SDC).
In 1966, Roberts became the chief scientist and in 1967 the director of the Information Processing Techniques Office (IPTO) of the Advanced Research Projects Agency (ARPA), later renamed the Defense Advanced Research Projects Agency (DARPA) of the United States Department of Defense (DoD). As director, Roberts was responsible for designing and managing the implementation of the Advanced Research Projects Agency Network (ARPANET) computer communications network, a research packet switching computer communications network that was the precursor to the internet.
In 1973, Roberts left IPTO to form the first commercial packet network, Telenet, where he held the position of Chief Executive Officer (CEO) until his departure in 1980. Starting in 1983, Roberts served as CEO of NetExpress and of Netmax Communications, president of ATM Systems, and founded Caspian Networks and Anagran Inc. while continuing his work with network technology. For the development of computer packet switching and network technology, Roberts received many honors and awards including the Charles Stark Draper prize (2001) and Secretary of Defense Meritorious Service Medal (1973).
Scope and Contents note
This collection documents the professional and research life of L. G. (Lawrence G.) Roberts who was the Advanced Research Projects Agency (ARPA) program manager responsible for designing and managing the implementation of the Advanced Research Projects Agency Network (ARPANET) in the late 1960s and early 1970s. The materials represent Robert's activities during the early period of development (1966-1973) of the packet computer network, ARPANET, started by the Department of Defense. The collection includes original data rate charts, logical and geographic maps, presentation slides, reports, conference itineraries, trade and scholarly publications, and correspondence relating to the cost, efficiency, research and development of the ARPANET. Materials dated later than 1973 consist primarily of special interest and trade publications which document the accomplishments of Roberts, the development of the ARPANET, and early computer networking history.
Arrangement note
The collection has been arranged in the following series:
Series 1: Network Notes and Diagrams, 1969-1988
Series 2: Correspondence, 1963-1973
Series 3: Publications, 1962-2009
Existence and Location of Copies
Digital reproductions of collection materials are available on the UCLA Digital Library | Kleinrock Center for Internet Studies.
Related Material
Leonard Kleinrock papers. Available at UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, UCLA.
Michael Allen Wingfield papers. Available at Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, UCLA.
Computer Science Department. Student papers, abstracts, and reports. 1965-1977. Available at Library Special Collections, University Archives, UCLA.
ARPANET (Computer network).; Roberts, L. G. (Lawrence G.) -- Archives; United States. Advanced Research Projects Agency
- Series 1: Network notes and diagrams, 1969-1988
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  PORTIONS OF THIS SERIES HAVE BEEN DIGITIZED. All requests to access special collections material must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
  Scope and Contents note
  Series 1 contains notes and diagrams relating to L. G. Roberts' work including calculations, diagrams, graphs, charts, logical and geographical maps, network topologies, presentations, project descriptions, cost analysis, data usage analysis, traffic analysis, and ARPANET reports.
  - Integrated Travel Reservation System, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    THESE ITEMS HAVE BEEN DIGITIZED. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
    Scope and Content
    This file contains sketches that propose an integrated travel reservation system.
  - ARPANET presentation, circa 1972 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    This file contains various diagrams and flow charts regarding the functionality of the ARPANET.
  - ARPANET notes (Box 1, Folder 1)
    This file contains evaluation notes of the ARPANET.
  - ARPANET network traffic notes (Box 1, Folder 1)
    This file contains documentation which describes ARPA Network traffic by participant organization.
  - ARPA Network data rates (Box 1, Folder 1)
    This file contains graphs which describe data rates for nodes within the ARPANET.
  - ARPANET graphs, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    This file contains graphs regarding throughput speed, ARPA Network cost vs. capacity, 21 node net, and actual ARPANET.
  - ARPANET node notes (Box 1, Folder 1)
    This file contains various notes and diagrams detailing the locations and connections between nodes of the ARPANET.
- Series 2: Correspondence, 1963-1973
  Series 2 contains correspondence relating to the professional activity of L. G. Roberts. This series includes original and duplicate incoming correspondence from the Intergalactic Computer Network, International Business Machines (IBM), and University of California's Office of the President.
  - Intergalactic Computer Network memorandum, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - IBM letter, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Letter to Roberts from Peter W. Markstein of International Business Machines (IBM) Corporation.
    THIS ITEM HAS BEEN DIGITIZED. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
  - University of California Data Communication letter, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Telenet Communications Corporation news release, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    A news release from Telenet Communications Corporation announcing Dr. Roberts' appointment as President and Chief Executive Officer.
- Series 3: Publications, 1962-2009
  This series contains conference papers, trade and scholarly publications, special interest publications, and ARPA publications documenting the evolution of ARPA network and development.
  - Publications by Roberts, 1966-2009 (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
    This file contains papers individually and jointly authored by Roberts.
  - Publications collected by Roberts, 1962-2001 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    This file includes publications regarding the history of the internet.